# Yasanka Sameera Horawalavithana

5022, Sunridge Palms Dr. Apt 204, Tampa, FL 33617 US Email: sameera1@usf.edu Web: https://samtube405.github.io/\_profile TP: +1 (813) 409-9303

## **OBJECTIVE**

My broad research interests are in **information diffusion**, **privacy and machine learning** on social network data. To this end, I have developed multiple analytical tools to understand social systems from the quantitative and/or computational perspective.

#### **EDUCATION**

# University of South Florida, Tampa, FL, USA

Ph.D. Candidate, Computer Science and Engineering GPA\*: 3.96 Estimated Graduation Date: Summer, 2021

University of Colombo, School of Computing, Colombo, Sri Lanka

Bachelor of Science (Hons.), Computer Science, April 2015, (Top 1%) GPA: 3.84

Umeå University, Sweden

Exchange Student, Computer Science, Fall 2013

# PROJECTS & PUBLICATIONS

Modeling Information Diffusion Processes with Deep Learning Algorithms (SocialSim, Funding Agency: DARPA)<sup>1</sup>, The objective of this work is to develop technologies for high-fidelity simulation of online social behavior (the spread and evolution of online information) while rigorously testing and measuring simulation accuracy in operational scenarios defined by Department of Defense, USA. We are designing novel methods to model the structure of information cascades in large scale social networks using Deep Learning techniques. *Technologies: Python, Large-scale Social Network Data Analysis (Twitter, YouTube, Reddit, GitHub, Telegram), Machine Learning algorithms*, (Jan 2018 - Present)

## $\rightarrow$ Data-driven Simulation

- 1. <u>Sameera Horawalavithana</u>, Nazim Choudhury, and Adriana Iamnitchi, Online Discussion Threads as Conversation Pools: Predicting the Growth of Discussion Threads on Reddit, Computational & Mathematical Organization Theory (CMOT) (*Under Review*).
- 2. <u>Sameera Horawalavithana</u>, Kin Wai NG, and Adriana Iamnitchi, Simulating Fine-Grained Twitter Activity during Political Crisis Using Exogenous Data, ACM Transactions on the Web (TWEB), 2021 (Under Review).
- 3. Kin Wai NG, <u>Sameera Horawalavithana</u>, and Adriana Iamnitchi, Social-Media Activity Forecasting with Exogenous Information Signals, IEEE/ACM International Conference on Advances in Social Networks Analysis and Mining (ASONAM), The Hague, Netherlands, 2021 (*Under Review*).
- 4. Renhao Liu, Fredrick Mubang, Lawrence O. Hall, <u>Sameera Horawalavithana</u>, Adriana Iamnitchi and John Skvoretz, Predicting Longitudinal User Activity at Fine Time Granularity in Online Collaborative Platforms, 2019 IEEE International Conference on Systems, Man and Cybernetics (SMC), Bari, Italy, 2019.

## $\rightarrow$ Social Networks Analysis

- Sameera Horawalavithana, Kin Wai NG, and Adriana Iamnitchi,. The Role of Social Bots in the China-Pakistan Economic Corridor Discussions on Twitter, The 32nd ACM Conference on Hypertext and Social Media (HT), 2021 (Under Review)
- 2. <u>Sameera Horawalavithana</u>, Kin Wai NG, and Adriana Iamnitchi, Drivers of Polarized Discussions on Twitter during Venezuela Political Crisis, The 13th International ACM Conference on Web Science (WebSci), 2021.
- 3. <u>Sameera Horawalavithana</u>, Ravindu De Silva, Mohamed Nabeel, Charitha Elvitigala, Primal Wijesekara, and Adriana Iamnitchi, Malicious and Low Credibility

<sup>&</sup>lt;sup>1</sup>http://www.cse.usf.edu/socialsim/

- URLs on Twitter during the AstraZeneca COVID-19 Vaccine Development, International Conference on Social Computing, Behavioral-Cultural Modeling, & Prediction and Behavior Representation in Modeling and Simulation (SBP-BRiMS), DC, USA, 2021
- 4. Kin Wai NG, <u>Sameera Horawalavithana</u>, and Adriana Iamnitchi, Multi-platform Information Operations: Twitter, Facebook and YouTube against the White Helmets, The Workshop Proceedings of the 14th International AAAI Conference on Web and Social Media, 2021.
- Sameera Horawalavithana, Kin Wai NG, and Adriana Iamnitchi,. Twitter is the Megaphone of Cross-Platform Messaging on the White Helmets, International Conference on Social Computing, Behavioral-Cultural Modeling, & Prediction and Behavior Representation in Modeling and Simulation (SBP-BRiMS), DC, USA, 2020
- Sameera Horawalavithana, Abhishek Bhattacharjee, Renhao Liu, Nazim Choudhury, Lawrence O. Hall, and Adriana Iamnitchi,. Mentions of Security Vulnerabilities in Reddit, Twitter and GitHub, IEEE/WIC/ACM International Conference on Web Intelligence, Thessaloniki, Greece, October, 2019

Structural Anonymization Techniques for Large, Labeled, and Dynamic Social Graphs (Funding Agency: NSF), The objective of this work is to provide big data owners with tools to safely share their social networks data with the research community. The project aims to approach graph anonymization via two techniques for graph generation: dK-series techniques, and Exponential Random Graph Model-based approaches (ERGM). Technologies: Python, R, Graph Generative Models, Statistical Models, Causality Analysis (Aug 2016 - Aug 2020)

- 1. <u>Sameera Horawalavithana</u>, Juan Arroyo Flores, John Skvoretz, and Adriana Iamnitchi. Behind the Mask: Understanding the Structural Forces that Make Social Graphs Vulnerable to De-anonymization. IEEE Transactions on Computational Social Systems (TCSS), 2019
- 2. <u>Sameera Horawalavithana</u>, Juan Arroyo Flores, John Skvoretz, and Adriana Iamnitchi. The Risk of Node Re-identification in Labeled Social Graphs, Applied Network Science (2019)
- Sameera Horawalavithana, Clayton Gandy, Juan Arroyo Flores, John Skvoretz, and Adriana Iamnitchi. Diversity, Topology, and the Risk of Node Re-identification in Labeled Social Graphs., The 7<sup>th</sup> International Conference on Complex Networks and Their Applications. Cambridge, UK, Dec. 2018

Group Dynamics in Online Games Modeling the behavior of online players to understand how groups form, and evolve dynamically (December 2016 - August 2019)

- Essa Alhazmi, <u>Sameera Horawalavithana</u>, Jeremy Blackburn, John Skvoretz and Adriana Iamnitchi. An Empirical Study on Team Formation in Online Games. In Proceedings of the IEEE/ACM International Conference on Advances in Social Networks Analysis and Mining (ASONAM), Australia, 2017
- 2. Essa Alhazmi, Naim Choudhury, <u>Sameera Horawalavithana</u> and Adriana Iamnitchi. Temporal Mobility Networks in Online Gaming. Frontiers in Big Data, 2019.

Top-k publish/subscribe model: Developed a content-based Top-k publish/subscribe model with a novel formalization of a ranking method that uses a variation of minimum-independent dominating set problem in dynamic graphs. Randomized algorithm is proposed to rank streaming contents. *Technologies: Java, Amazon Kinesis, Amazon ElasticCache.* (March 2014 - December 2014)

Sameera Horawalavithana and D. N. Ranasinghe. 2015. An Efficient Incremental Indexing Mechanism for Extracting Top-k Representative Queries Over Continuous Data-streams. In Proceedings of the 14th International Workshop on Adaptive and Reflective Middleware (ARM) colocated with USENIX Middleware, Vancouver, Canada, December, 2015

2. Sameera Horawalavithana, D.N. Ranasinghe. Cloud based pub/sub model for Top-k matching over continuous data-streams [Best Undergraduate Thesis] January 2015, University of Colombo, School of Computing, Sri Lanka

Real-time ETL: Contributed to the development of a (near) real-time data-warehouse solution during my tenure at Sysco Labs, Technologies: Java, Apache Storm, Hadoop Eco-system, MySQL (February 2015 - August 2015)

#### INVITED TALKS

- 1. Sameera Horawalavithana, Lessons from Developing Data-driven Simulators of Information Spread in Social Media, Networks, 2021
- 2. Generative/Discriminative Approach to De-construct Cascading Events, Machine Learning in Network Science, NetSci, 2019

### **EXPERIENCE**

# Graduate Research Assistant

University of South Florida Department: CSE

Sysco Labs (Pvt.) Ltd.

January 2017 - Present Currently working at Distributed System Group (DSG) under Adriana Iamnitchi.

Software Engineer February 2015 - July 2016 59, Flower Rd, Colombo 07, Sri Lanka Worked at Data and Analytic Team.

Guest Lecturer University of Colombo July 2015, 2016 35, Reid Avenue, Colombo 07, Sri Lanka

Course: Distributed System, MSc

# AWARDS & **HONORS**

- Winner, Grand Challenge, COVID-19 AstraZeneca Vaccine Disinformation, The 3rd North American Social Networks Conference (NASN), 2021
- Best Computer Science Undergraduate Thesis Award in the year 2014, University of Colombo, Sri Lanka
- Linnaeus Palme Scholarship on the International Exchange Programme administered by the International Programme Office for Education and Training and financed by Sida, Swedish International Development Co-operation Agency.
- o Scholarship to attend Summer Institute, San Diego Super Computing Center (SDSC), University of California, San Diego, Summer, 2018
- $\circ$  Scholarship to attend  $2^{nd}$  International summer school for Deep Learning, University of Genoa, Genoa, Italy, Summer, 2018
- ACM/SIGHPC Travel Grant for Supercomputing conference 2016, Utah
- o Achieved 3rd place at Nordic Collegiate Programming Contest 2013 (Umeå region) representing Umeå university, Sweden
- o Mahapola Merit Higher Education Scholarship, Government of Sri Lanka, 2010-2015

# **TEACHING & MENTORSHIP**

Google Summer of Code (GSoC) Mentorship I served as an advisor to the opensource organization, Sustainable Computing Research Lab (SCoRe), where I mentored two GSoC students to implement a crowd sourced fact checking platform. The goal of this platform (FactBounty) is to promote the civic participation to minimize the spread of false news and rumors in Sri Lankan digital eco-system.

- Anmol Bansal, Implement a backend for a crowd-driven Fact-checking platform.
- Tuan Amith, A web interface for a crowd-driven Fact-checking platform.

## Research Supervision (Undergraduate)

- Milindu Sanoj Kumarage (2015), An efficient query platform for streaming and dynamic natural graphs, University of Colombo, Sri Lanka
- Malith Senaweera, Ruwanmalee Dissanayake, Nuwini Chamindi, (2017), The Influence of Community Interactions on User Affinity in Social Networks: A Facebook Case Study, University of Colombo, Sri Lanka

# Teaching Assistant

Network Science, (Graduate-level, Fall, 2018), Data Structures (Undergraduate-level, Fall, 2016), University of South Florida. Prepared and evaluated homework assignments, held weekly recitations and office hours

### Student Volunteer

Volunteer on organization activities at ACM Symposium on Principles of Distributed Computing (PODC) conference, Washington, DC, Summer 2017

# SERVICE (PC/Reviewing)

- o International Workshop on Social Sensing (SocialSens), ICWSM, 2021
- IEEE Transactions on Computational Social Systems (TCSS), 2020.
- IEEE Transactions on Information Forensics & Security (TFIS), 2020
- $\circ\,$  Journal of Computational Social Science, Springer, 2020
- o Transactions on Parallel and Distributed Systems (TPDS), 2018.
- o Online Social Networks and Media (OSNEM), Elsevier Journal, 2018
- $\circ$  IEEE International Conference on Distributed Computing Systems (ICDCS), 2018

# **DECLARATION**

I hereby declare that the above written particulars are true to the best of my knowledge and belief & below referees can be contacted to get further information.

Prof. Adriana Iamnitchi,

Professor (Ph.D. Advisor),

Department of Computer Science and Engineering, University of South Florida anda@cse.usf.edu

Prof. John Skvoretz, Department of Sociology, University of South Florida jskvoretz@usf.edu Distinguished Professor,

Prof. Lawrence O. Hall, Distinguished Professor, Department of Computer Science and Engineering, University of South Florida lohall@mail.usf.edu